A Guide to the John Randall Cook Papers, 1910-2012
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
John Randall Cook Papers, 1910-2012
The Library of Virginia
50648
3.825 cubic feet (9 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John Randall Cook, Richmond.
Biographical Information
Dr. John Randall Cook was born in Crewe, Nottoway County, Virginia on 12 September 1919. He is the son of William Manning Cook (1890-1954) and Madeline Inez Bryant (1893-1979). He attended St. Joseph's Academy in St. Augustine, Florida (1940) and Georgetown University (1946-1948). Dr. Cook served with the Army Medical Corps during World War II, and was stationed at the First General Hospital near London, and when it moved near Paris. Dr. Cook earned a bachelor's degree in English (1952), a master's degree in Education (1960), and was presented with an honorary doctor of letters degree by Longwood University (1996). He was employed as a guidance counselor at John Marshall High School in Richmond, Virginia (1960-1966), and then was supervisor of guidance with the Virginia Department of Education (1967-1982). Dr. Cook, with his partner Dr. Waverly Manson Cole (1929-2009), has been an active supporter of various causes and educational institutions in Virginia. He published his autobiography Many Septembers in 2007. Dr. Cook died on 24 December 2013 and is buried in Crewe Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1910-2012, of Dr. John Randall Cook (1919-2013) of Richmond, Virginia, relating to his service in the Army Medical Corps during World War II, his career as a guidance counselor at John Marshall High School and the Virginia Department of Education, and the publication of his autobiography Many Septembers (2007). There are also materials concerning philanthropic support by Dr. Cook and his partner Dr. Waverly Manson Cole (1929-2009) of The College of William and Mary, Longwood University, and Virginia Commonwealth University, as well as information on their real estate holdings in Virginia Beach. The collection includes articles and reports, clippings, correspondence, greeting cards, invitations, military records, newsletters, photographs, poetry, programs, and speeches.
Contents List
- Albright, Arnold A.. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American School Counselor Association - Supervisor of the Year Award. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Biographical Information/Vita. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Blackstone College - "The Gables". (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Certificates. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- College of William and Mary. (Box 1, Folder 8-13)
- Community Foundation. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Cook, William Manning - Funeral Book. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1910. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1916. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1919. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1925. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1935. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1937. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1938. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1939. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1941. (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1942. (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1943. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1944 (January-March). (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1944 (April-May). (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1944 (June-July). (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1944 (August-September). (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1944 (October-December). (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1945. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1946. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1947. (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1950. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1951. (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1952. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1954. (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1955. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Correspondence, 1957. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Correspondence, 1958. (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Correspondence, 1959. (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1960. (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Correspondence, 1968. (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Correspondence, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Correspondence, 1970. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Correspondence, 1974. (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Correspondence, 1979. (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Correspondence, 1980. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1983. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1985. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1986. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1987. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1988. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1990. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1993. (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1995. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1996. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 2000. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 2001. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 2002. (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 2003. (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 2004. (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 2005. (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 2006. (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 2007. (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 2008. (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 2009. (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 2010. (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 2011. (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 2012. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Correspondence - McGrath, Betty Zim. (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
- Correspondence and Poems to Dr. Waverly Cole. (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Correspondence, undated. (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Democratic Club of Virginia - Minutes, 1959. (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Estate of Madeline Bryant Cook. (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Estate of William M. Cook. (Box 3, Folder 31)
- First General Hospital. (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
- Funeral Programs/Eulogies. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Gardner Family Bible Record (Franklin County, VA). (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Gay Rights Organizations. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Genealogy. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Glass and Porcelain Collections (Longwood University). (Box 4, Folder 8-12)
- Greeting Cards. (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Greeting Cards. (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
- Guidance and Education - Articles, Reports, etc.. (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Guidance and Education - Reports (John R. Cook). (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Historic Richmond Foundation. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- John Marshall High School. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Jokes. (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Legisltion. (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Letters of Recommendation. (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Longwood University. (Box 5, Folder 11-13)
- Many Septembers (Two Copies). (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Many Septembers - Correspondence. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Many Septembers - Data. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Many Septembers - Data Not Used. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Many Septembers - Draft. (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
- McFatter, Emma Rouse. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 9)
- "My Name is Edith". (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Obituaries. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Passports. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Photographs - Building Interiors/Exteriors. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Photographs - Career and Awards. (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Photographs - Dogs. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Photographs - Family. (Box 7, Folder 4-6)
- Photographs - Friends and Acquaintances. (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
- Photographs - Vacations. (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
- Photographs - WWII. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Poetry. (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Poetry Scrapbook. (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Political Leaders. (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Real Estate. (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Real Estate - Rental Book. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Real Estate - 1308 Grove Avenue. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Real Estate - "Merrygold" - 207 55th Street. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Real Estate - "Needlepoint" - 212 74th Street. (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Real Estate - "Pinetag". (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Real Estate - "Pineview" - 216 79th Street. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Respess, Iowa Gardner - Funeral Book. (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Richmond Symphony. (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Speeches. (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Speeches (John R. Cook). (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Telegrams. (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Margaret Thatcher. (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Virginia Commonwealth University. (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Virginia Commonwealth University. (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
- Virginia Department of Education. (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
- Virginia Personnel and Guidance Association - Career Service Award. (Box 9, Folder 5)